Guide to the Jan Erik Bouman Collection of James Purdy YCAL MSS 1510
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Jan Erik Bouman collection of James Purdy
1977-2006
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Bouman, Jan Erik
YCAL MSS 1510
2.21 Linear Feet 3 boxes
This collection contains writings of American author James Purdy, correspondence of Purdy and Dutch printer Jan Erik Bouman, photographs, drawings and a sketchbook by Purdy, ephemera, printed material, and computer media. Writings include typescript drafts of poems, novels, plays, and shorter works by Purdy, as well as published versions of Purdy's poems issued by Bouman's Utrecht-based press Hugin & Munin.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Box 3 (DVD): Restricted fragile material. Access copies of digital files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Rene Hesselink, 2011.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. James Purdy Writings, 1977-2004. II. Correspondence, 1984-2006, undated. III. Computer Media, 2004.
Jan Erik Bouman (1947-2010)
Jan Erik Bouman was a Dutch printer and friend of American writer James Purdy. He operated the small press Hugin & Munin in Utrecht, Netherlands, from 1995 until his death. Bouman printed several works by Purdy.
James Purdy (1914-2009)
James Purdy was an American author, poet, translator, and playwright. His early works include the short story collections 63: Dream Palace (1956) and Color of Darkness (1961), and the novels Malcolm (1959), which was adapted for the stage by Edward Albee in 1966, and Eustace Chisholm and the Works (1967). As a playwright, Purdy's best-known work is Cracks, produced Off-Broadway in 1963. His later works include Collected Poems (1990), Out with the Stars (1992), and Moe's Villa and Other Stories (2000, 2005).
Scope and Contents
This collection contains writings of American author James Purdy, correspondence of Purdy and Dutch printer Jan Erik Bouman, photographs, drawings and a sketchbook by Purdy, ephemera, printed material, and computer media. Writings include typescript drafts of poems, novels, plays, and shorter works by Purdy, as well as published versions of Purdy's poems issued by Bouman's Utrecht-based press Hugin & Munin.
American literature -- 20th Century; Born digital; Photographs; Sketchbooks; Authors -- United States -- 20th Century; Dramatists -- United States -- 20th Century; American poetry -- 20th Century; Novelists -- United States -- 20th Century; Poets -- United States -- 20th Century; Printers -- Netherlands -- 20th Century; Bouman, Jan Erik; Purdy, James, 1914-2009; Hugin & Munin (Firm)
- James Purdy Writings, 1977-2004; 1 Linear Feet (1 box)
  Scope and Contents
  This series primarily contains typescript and photocopied drafts of poems, plays, novels, and shorter works by James Purdy, including Collected Poems, "Moe's Villa," and Foment, as well as correspondence, ephemera, reviews, agreements with Jan Erik Bouman, and poems of Purdy printed by Hugin & Munin.
  Arrangement
  Not arranged in any particular order.
  Related Materials
  Associated materials: Writings can also be found in Series II. Correspondence.
  - Are You in the Wintertree, with related correspondence and other documents, 1985-1987; 1 Folders (Box 1)
  - The Blue House: Forbidden Poems, with letters from Purdy to Bouman, 2000-2004; 1 Folders (Box 1)
  - "Brawith", 1993; 1 Folders (Box 1)
  - Collected Poems, 1987; 1 Folders (Box 1)
  - Works by James Purdy in Dutch, 1984, undated; 1 Folders (Box 1)
  - "Enduring Zeal", 1990; 1 Folders (Box 1)
  - Foment, 1990; 1 Folders (Box 1)
  - Foment, bound typescript, 1990; 1 Folders (Box 1)
  - Garments the Living Wear, 1987; 1 Folders (Box 1)
  - In the Night of Time, 1991; 1 Folders (Box 1)
  - "Moe's Villa", 1997; 1 Folders (Box 1)
  - The Paradise Circus, 1991 April 1; 1 Folders (Box 1)
  - "Plays", 1980s; 2 Folders (Box 1)
  - "James Purdy poems and stories," with photocopied reviews, 1977-2000; 1 Folders (Box 1)
  - The Rivalry of Dolls, bound typescript, 1990; 1 Folders (Box 1)
  - Ruthiana Elder, with autograph dedication, 1989; 1991 April 8; 1 Folders (Box 1)
  - Running the Sun, 1990; 1 Folders (Box 1)
  - Untitled, 1993 February 20-1994 February 3; 1 Folders (Box 1)
  - "The White Blackbird," "Mi Chiecle Sepre," and Dutch newspaper clipping, 1980s-1990s; 1 Folders (Box 1)
  - Out with the Stars, photocopied proof, 1992; 1 Folders (Box 1)
  - Where Quentin Goes, "copy 2", 1991; 1 Folders (Box 1)
- Correspondence, 1984-2006, undated; 1 Linear Feet (1 box)
  Arranged alphabetically by correspondent, with empty envelopes filed at the end of the sequence.
  Associated materials: Correspondence can also be found in Series I. James Purdy Writings.
  This series contains correspondence between James Purdy and Jan Erik Bouman, as well as writings and artwork by Purdy, photographs, clippings, and ephemera. Included are copies of satirical sketches and mock press releases, letters, and news stories composed by Purdy.
  - Bouman to Purdy, 1992-2006; 1 Folders (Box 2)
  - Purdy to Bouman, 1984-1988; 1 Folders (Box 2)
  - Purdy to Bouman, 1989-1992; 1 Folders (Box 2)
  - Purdy to Bouman, 1993-1999; 1 Folders (Box 2)
  - Purdy - "documents, drawings, fotographs [sic], correspondence (not dated)", 1985-2000; 2 Folders (Box 2)
  - Envelopes (empty) to Bouman, circa 1984-1988; 2 Folders (Box 2)
  - Envelopes (empty) to Bouman, circa 1989-2002; 2 Folders (Box 2)
  - Envelopes (empty) to Bouman, circa 1993-2000; 2 Folders (Box 2)
  - Small envelopes (empty) to Bouman, circa 1990-2000; 1 Folders (Box 2)
  - Large envelopes (empty) to Bouman, circa 1985-2004; 1 Folders (Box 2)
- Computer Media, 2004; .21 Linear Feet (1 box)
  This series consists of one DVD containing Dutch television interviews of James Purdy, Gore Vidal, Paul Bowles, and Raymond Carver.
  - DVD - The Jan Erik Collection, 2004 (Box 3)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Restricted fragile material. Access copies of digital files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.